《福尔摩斯历险记》
《银额马》
事情不妙 我必须要去一趟
It's no good. I shall have to go.
去一趟？去哪？
Go? Go where?
金斯皮兰
King's Pyland.
昨天晚上德文郡警局的格雷戈里督察
Last evening Inspector Gregory of the Devonshire Constabulary
逮捕了知名的赛马人菲茨罗·伊辛普森
arrested well known racing personality Fitzroy Simpson
并且控诉他谋杀了驯马师约翰·斯特拉
and charged him with the murder of trainer, John Straker…
哦 请进
Oh, come in.
又有两封电报 福尔摩斯先生
Two more telegrams, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢你 哈德森太太
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
你这两天一直在 又是格雷戈里督察发来的
You've been bombarded with these the last couple of days.
和一封罗斯上校的
A note from Colonel Ross.
哇 那是马的主人
Awe, that's the horse's owner.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you my dear.
华生
Watson,
我犯了一个大错
I had made a blunder,
是那些只读了你的传记
which I am afraid is a more common occurrence
而知道我的人
than anyone would think
不会想到的一件常事
who only knew me through your memoirs.
不过事实是我不敢相信
But the fact is that I could not believe
像银额马这样一匹一眼就能认出的马
that so a remarkable a horse as Silver Blaze
会就这么消失
could disappear,
特别是在像达特穆尔 这样的僻静之地
especially in the seclusion of somewhere like Dartmoor.
我无时无刻都希望可以听到消息
From hour to hour I expect to hear that the abductor
那个拐马者就是杀害约翰·斯特拉的凶手
was the murderer of John Straker
而且马也找回来了
and the horse had been found
但是看上去不是这么回事
but that doesn't seem to be the case.
我会很乐意跟你一起去
I should be happy to go with you.
不 在塔维斯托克呢
No, Tavistock.
如果我不妨碍你的话
If I should not be in the way.
哦 我亲爱的华生
Oh my dear Watson,
你愿意同去是对我很大的支持
you would confer a great favour upon me by coming.
我相信不会浪费你的时间
I'm sure your time will not be misspent.
我保证这绝对是件独一无二的案子
The case promises to be absolutely unique.
我们正好能赶上去帕丁顿的火车
We can just catch our train from Paddington.
哦 华生 你可以带上
Oh Watson, would you be so kind as to bring
你的双筒望远镜吗
your field glasses?
哈德森太太 我们要去达特穆尔
Mrs. Hudson, were off to Dartmoor.
请出示车票
Tickets please.
谢谢你 巡票员
Thank you, Inspector.
谢谢
Thank you.
华生 我们今天的速度不错
Watson, we're going well.
现在的速度是
Our speed at present is
每小时五十三英里半
fifty-three and half miles an hour.
我没留心去数每隔四分之一英里的路杆
I've not observed the quarter mile post.
我也没有
Nor have I.
但是这条铁路边的电线杆的间隔
But the telegraphed posts on this line
是六十码
are sixty yards apart.
这是很简单的计算
The calculation is a simple one.
那份受人瞩目 喜欢过度渲染的体育报纸
Has that remarkably, colored, sporting paper
提到了任何关于我们的马的事吗
anything to say on the subject of our horse?
什么？
What?
哦 有的
Oh, yes.
好
Yes.
在这里
Here we are.
银额马
Silver Blaze.
银额马拥有索默密的血统
Silver Blaze is from lsonomy stock.
索默密
Isonomy…
而且像它著名的祖先一样
And holds as brilliant a record
保持着辉煌的记录
as his famous ancestor.
它现在五岁了
He's now in his fifth year
每次都能在赛马场上 为他幸运的主人
and has brought in turn each of the prize of the turf
罗斯上校赢得奖金
to Colonel Ross his fortunate owner.
眼下灾难发生之际
At the time of the catastrophe
它是威塞克斯杯中最有望夺冠的一匹
he was first favored for the Wessex Cup.
赔率是二比一
The odds quoted being two to one against.
作为赛马嗜好者一向最爱的宠驹
He's always been a prime favorite of the racing public
从来没有让他们失望过
and has never yet disappointed them.
尽管赌注悬殊
In spite of the unfavorable prize,
还是有巨款押在了它身上
a great deal of money has been placed upon him
所以很明显 许多人出于
so it is obvious, therefore, that there are
自身利益的考量 会想方设法
many people with the strongest interest in preventing Silver Blaze
阻止银额马出赛
from being there at the fall of the flag.
好吧 贝恩斯 请在这里停一下
All right, Baynes, will you stop here please,
这里的风景不错
cause this is a rather good view.
那边就是金斯皮兰 福尔摩斯先生
Now that's King's Pyland over there Mr. Holmes.
我的驯马厩
You know my training stable where the missing horse was kept.
那处是驯马师的房子
Well, there's the trainer's house,
可怜的斯特拉克和他的老婆住在一起
where poor Straker lived with his wife
还有一个女仆
and a maidservant.
他跟在你身边多久了 先生
How long had he been with you sir?
哦 当了我五年的骑师
Oh, five years at jockey
直到他发福无法再上马
until he got too heavy for the weighing chair.
接下来七年做了我的驯马师
Then seven years as my trainer.
是的 他水平一流
Yes, he was a first class man.
我猜更远处就是马厩
And I presume the stables are beyond?
是的 马场不大但是很不错
Yes, yes not a big yard, it's a good one.
我注重的是质量不是数量
My thought is quality not quantity.
在赛马场上活跃的人都可以
As anyone connected with the turf will
告诉你这点 福尔摩斯先生
tell you, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢 督察 你看 现在
Yes, thank you, Inspector. You see,
马场里只养了五匹马
at the moment I'm merely five horses in the yard.
我知道你让其中两匹
I see you have two of them
参加了威塞克斯杯 罗斯上校
entered for the Wessex Cup, Colonel Ross.
没错 是的 银额马和贝阿得
That's right, yes. Yes, Silver Blaze and Bayard.
可别说出去 派上贝阿得是为了去领跑
But between us Bayard is intended for a pacemaker.
训练这么名贵的动物
Well with such valuable animals under his charge,
我想你的驯马师斯特拉克先生
I imagine your trainer Mr. Straker
一定采取了一些预防措施
must have taken some precautions.
哦 没有错
Oh yes indeed.
有三个小马倌和马匹一起生活
Three stable lads lived with the horses
天黑之后其中一个 会在马厩值班
and after dark one of the lads was always on duty in the stables
其他两个会睡在阁楼里
while the other two sleep above in loft.
那边是不是还有一个驯马场？
Is that another training stable over there?
是的 那里是梅普尔顿
Yes, that's Mapleton.
布莱克沃特勋爵的马场
Lord Backwater's yard.
布莱克沃特勋爵？
Lord Backwater?
布莱克沃特勋爵有匹德丝贝里
Lord Backwater owns Desberly,
是威塞克斯杯的二号种子吧
second favorite for the Wessex Cup.
是匹不错的马
This is not a bad horse.
但和银额马不是一个等级的
Not in the same class as Silver Blaze.
那个人叫西拉斯·布朗
Fellow called, Silas Brown,
是贝克华特的驯马师 谜一样的人
trains for Backwater, I can't stick the fellow himself.
连斯特拉克也搞不懂他
Nor could Straker come to that.
我想是竞争对手的缘故吧
There's a natural rivalry I presume.
不止如此
Rather more than that.
我们可以继续走了吗？
Shall we drive on?
好的
Yes, indeed.
走了 贝恩斯
All right, Baynes.
格雷戈里督察
Inspector Gregory,
对马匹去向的调查
are there any further developments as to
有没有进展？
the whereabouts of the horse?
完全没有
Nothing at all.
我们在这个方面 几乎停滞不前
We have made very little progress in that direction.
我不能想象像这样一匹银额马
I can't imagine how a horse like Silver Blaze
会在这样的地方失踪
could go missing for so long in a place like this.
我也想不到
Nor can I.
我必须告诉你 福尔摩斯先生
I must tell you Mr. Holmes,
我一开始并不完全接受
that at first I was not at all taken
格雷戈里督察的建议
with Inspector Gregory's suggestion
把你请到这里来
that you should be asked to come down here.
我不喜欢业余的 明白吗？
I don't like amateurs, you see?
哈
Ha.
但是你还是给我发了电报 上校
But you did send me a telegram, Colonel.
看来没有别人可以找到我的马了
Well no one else seems to be able to find my horse.
如果你问我会是谁 我会说是那些散居在
If you ask me it's these damn gypsies
荒野上的该死的吉普赛浪人
wondering all over the moor.
早晚会出丑事 我说这话很多年了
It's a perfect scandal, I've said so for years.
我的人在过去的两天中
My men have seen every group
调查了在达特穆尔的
of gypsies on Dartmoor
每个吉普赛人 上校
in the last two days, Colonel.
而且搜查了南德文郡的每个马厩
And searched every stable yard, quarry
采石场和洞穴
and cave in south Devon.
这绝对是一个迷
It's an absolute mystery.
我期待你能创造奇迹 福尔摩斯先生
I expect a miracle from you, Mr. Holmes.
格雷戈里督察
Inspector Gregory,
我在苏格兰场的朋友跟我说
my friends at Scotland Yard tell me
你迅速地建立了自己的声誉
that you're rapidly making a reputation for yourself
在英国侦探圈中
in the English detective service.
我也是个热心学习您办案方法的学生
I'm a keen student of your methods too,
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
我有两个主要证人在等您
I have the two principle, witnesses waiting for you.
谢谢
Thank you.
在这里 福尔摩斯先生
In here, Mr. Holmes.
他们是谁？
Who are they?
女仆伊迪丝·巴克斯特
Edith Baxter, the maid and
值班的马童亨特
Hunter, the stable boy
以及在星期一晚上
who was on duty on Monday night.
那是九点刚过几分 先生
It was just a few minutes after nine o'clock, sir.
我端着亨特先生的晚餐
I was carrying Mr. Hunter supper across from the house.
晚餐吃的是什么呢
what did the supper consist of?
是一盘咖喱羊肉 先生
It was a dish of curried mutton, sir.
突然我听见了一个男人的声音
Suddenly I heard a man's voice.
我可以告诉你 先生 我完全没有心理准备
Did not give me a turn, I can tell you sir.
不好意思 小姐
Excuse me, Miss.
你想干什么 先生
What do you want, sir?
你能告诉我这是哪里吗
Can you tell me where I am?
就在我几乎决定露宿荒野的时候
I'd almost made up my mind to sleep on the moor
看见了这里的灯光
when I saw the light.
这里是金斯皮兰驯马场 先生
This is King's Pyland training stable, sir.
那真是太走运了
What a stroke of luck.
我知道会有小马倌晚上睡在里面
I understand there's stable lad who sleeps here at night.
毫无疑问你端的是他的晚餐了
No doubt that's his supper you have there.
我相信你不会那么骄傲
I'm sure you wouldn't be too proud
连一条新裙子的钱也不屑赚吧
to earn yourself the price of a new dress would you?
看 今晚把这个给那男孩
See the boy has this tonight
你就能得到可以买一条最漂亮的
and you shall have the prettiest frock money can buy.
我不能要
I couldn't!
内德
Ned!
外面有一个男人拦住了我
There's a man stopped me out there.
我很害怕
I'm ever so frightened.
他想干什么
What did he want?
他问起了你
He asked after you.
让我给你一些东西
He asked me to give you something.
是什么
What was it?
我不知道 是一样白色的东西
I don't know. It was white.
他现在在哪
Where is he now?
他走了
He's gone.
你最好马上回屋去告诉老爷
We best cut back to the house. Quick tell the governor!
好的 内德
Yes Ned.
晚上好 我想和你说几句话
Good evening I want a word with you.
你来这里有什么事
What business have you here?
是件能让你的口袋
It's a business that may put something
鼓起来的买卖 小伙子
in your pocket, my lad.
你现在有两匹参加威塞克斯杯的马
Now you've two horses entering the Wessex Cup,
银额马和贝阿得
Silver Blaze and Bayard.
给我透点内幕 不会对你有坏处
Let me have the straight tip and you won't be the loser.
贝阿得真的可以在
Is it the fact that at the weights Bayard
五弗隆的距离里
can give the other a hundred yards
超过银额马一百码吗？
and five furlongs in the…
你别想从我这里得到任何消息 滚
You wont get any tips around here, get out!
追上他 追上他
After him boy, after him!
老爷和其他人已经来得很及时了
The governor and the others came down soon enough.
但我们没有找到那个男人的半点踪迹
We found not a sight or sound of the man.
等一下
One moment.
你把狗放出去之后
When you let the dog out did you leave
门有没有关上？
the door open behind you?
问得好 华生 问得好
Oh excellent, Watson, excellent.
这正是我要问的
It's just the point I was going to make.
我把门锁上了 先生 我发誓
I locked the door behind me sir. I swear it.
好孩子
Good lad.
菲茨罗·伊辛普森认罪了吗？
Does Fitzroy Simpson admit to all this?
他对此全盘否认
He denies nothing.
他说来这是为了买消息
He says he came for information…
那张白条是什么？
What about the white paper?
他说那是一张五镑纸币
He says it was a five-pound note.
接下来发生了什么
What happened next?
先生
Well sir,
那是天刚亮的时候
it was about dawn when
女主人走进我的卧室
the mistress came into my bedroom
叫我跟她走
and told me to come with her.
当她醒来时
Well when she woke
发现斯特拉克先生的床是空的
she'd found Mr. Straker's bed empty.
天啊 马不见了
Heavens! The horse is gone…
还有马勒
And the bridle.
内德 醒醒
Ned, wake up!
把他叫醒
Wake the boys.
内德 内德 醒醒 醒醒 内德
Ned! Ned! Wake up. Wake up, Ned!
比尔 罗比 快来 银额马不见了
Bill, Robbie come quick, Silver Blaze is gone.
这边
Over here.
他死了 先生
He was dead sir.
他的头
His head,
被打得陷进去了一块
it was all knocked in.
实在是太可怕了
It was terrible.
头部受到了
It was a terrible blow on the head
这就是他的死因 某种钝器的重击
from some blunt instrument that had killed him.
很明显 他曾拼命抵抗过
It was clear that he had defended himself most vigorously.
一把血迹斑斑的小刀
The blood stained knife.
和大腿上伤口 你们说呢
As to the wound on the thigh, who can tell?
腿上的伤口可能是
Well it is possible that the wound on the thigh
斯特拉克摔倒的时候造成的
could have been caused as Straker fell.
那个男孩被下药了
The lad here was drugged.
在他的咖喱中有
Appreciable quantities of powered opium
一定分量的麻醉药
were found in his carry.
所有人吃得都是一样的吗
Did all the household eat the same dish?
是的 先生 我亲自下厨再端上餐桌
Yes sir, I made it myself and served it.
这条黑红色的围巾
This black and red scarf?
那位先生跟我说话时
The gentleman was wearing that scarf
我可以在圣经面前发誓 先生
when he talked to me.
谢谢你 华生
Thank you Watson.
谢谢
Thank you.
别这样 别这样
Stop it boy. Stop it.
来吧 乖狗狗
Come on. Good dog.
乖狗狗
Good boy.
我的理论是
My theory is
辛普森是想方设法收买情报
that Simpson was under some strong
或者用别的法子让马无法上场
obligation to Nobble or otherwise incapacitate this horse
不能参加威塞克斯杯
so that he would be unable to run in the Wessex Cup.
在男孩的饭里下麻醉药倒是挺聪明
Clever move that, putting opium in the boy's food
利用那窗户很容易得手
and easy enough through that window.
是的 下面就简单了
Yes. Then it was simple.
他用一把复制好的钥匙 把马牵了出去
He obtained a duplicate key, led out the horse,
但他运气不好 斯特拉克很警觉
it was his bad luck that Straker was alert enough to
追踪他到了野外
catch him up on the moor,
在对抗中 马逃走了
in the struggle the horse bolted.
没有证据说明
That's no proof
辛普森杀了斯特拉克
that Simpson killed Straker.
我们有足够对他不利的证据
Well the evidence against him is very strong.
毫无疑问他来这有不可告人的目的
He was undoubtedly here on some devious business.
他给马倌下了毒
He poisoned the stable lad.
他手上有一根很沉的铅头手杖
He had in his hand a heavy stick weighted with lead
而且在死者的手上有他的围巾
and his scarf was found in the dead man's hand
当我用这些和他对质时
And he went pale as death
我真的认为在陪审团面前 证据是游刃有余了
when I confronted him with that fact.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
督察 一个聪明点的律师完全可以把它们驳倒
Inspector, a cleaver council would tear it all to rags.
在他身上发现了复制钥匙吗
Has a duplicate key been found in his possession?
没有
No.
更重要的是
And above all how could he,
一个陌生人是怎么在这里把一匹马藏起来了
a stranger in this district, hide a horse
更何况是一匹这样的银额马
and such a horse as Silver Blaze?
我同意证据都是间接的
I agree the evidence is circumstantial
但我认为布在
but I think the net is
菲茨罗·伊辛普森周围的网很紧密
drawn pretty tightly around Fitzroy Simpson
我相信他已经是网中鱼
and I believe he is our man.
他是一个怎样的人？
What sort of fellow is he and
为什么会做出这种事呢？
why would he do such a thing?
菲茨罗·伊辛普森 出身于名门望族
Fitzroy Simpson is a man of excellent birth and dedication.
很不幸地他在赛马场上输掉了一大笔财富
Unfortunately he has squandered a fortune on the turf,
导致他负债累累
which has put him in the hands of moneylenders
并且成为一个不择手段的赌马人
and unscrupulous bookmakers.
在赛马场上确实有这样的人
Plenty of those sharks in the racing world.
我不知道你也会赌 华生
I didn't know that you were a betting man, Watson.
什么？我只是偶尔在赛马上下笔小赌注
What? Oh, just the occasional flutter.
我猜你们有了份
I presume an inventory has been made
斯特拉克死时 他口袋里东西的清单
of what Straker had in his pockets at the time of his death?
东西就在 我的客厅里
I have the things themselves in the sitting room.
如果你想看的话
if you would care to see them.
伦敦韦斯公司
Weiss & Co., London.
从血迹来看 我猜
From the bloodstains, I presume,
这就是死者 抓着的刀
this is the knife that was found in the dead man's grasp.
没错
Yes indeed.
这更接近你的专业 医生
This is more in your line, Doctor.
是我们所称的为眼翳刀
This is what we call a cataract knife.
非常锋利的刀刃
Very delicate blade devised
专门用于非常精密的手术
for very delicate work.
会有人如此随身携带
Strange thing for a man to take on
可真稀奇 福尔摩斯
so rough an expedition, Holmes,
怎么会没有戳破他的口袋呢
especially as it wouldn't shut in his pocket.
在尸体旁 我们找到了
Awe, the tip was guarded by a disc of cork,
小刀的软木圆鞘
which we found beside the body.
你很出色 督察
You impress me, Inspector.
谢谢 斯特拉克夫人说原来
Thank you. Mrs. Straker says
它是放在梳妆台上
it was on the dressing table.
这可能是 他当时最随手可得的东西了
It was probably the nearest thing to him at the time.
我明白了
I see.
马料商的账单
Corn merchants bill.
罗斯上校的指示信
Instructions from Colonel Ross.
这个又是什么？
Awe what have we here?
一张女衣店账单 三十七镑十五先令
A milliner's account for 37 pounds fifteen shillings
伦敦邦德街 莱苏丽尔夫人开具
for a Madame Lesurier, of Bond Street, London,
给 德比郡的威廉先生
to a Mr. William Derbyshire.
斯特拉克女士告诉我们
Mrs. Straker tells us
德比郡是他丈夫的一个朋友
that Derbyshire was a friend of her husband's
偶尔他的信 会寄到这里
and on occasionally had his letters addressed here.
二十二几尼
Twenty-two guineas.
对一件衣服来说贵了点
Somewhat heavy for a single costume.
德比郡夫人喜欢贵的东西
Mrs. Derbyshire had rather expensive taste.
是的
Yes.
看来没有其他有用的东西了 督察
Well there appears to be nothing more to learn here, Inspector,
我们去犯罪现场吧
shall we move onto the scene of the crime?
好的 当然
Yes, of course.
你先 华生
After you Watson.
你抓住他们了吗 督察
Have you got them, Inspector?
有什么新消息吗？
Is there any more news?
恐怕没有 斯特拉克夫人
I'm afraid not, Mrs. Straker.
但是福尔摩斯先生和华生医生
But Mr. Holmes and Doctor Watson
从伦敦赶来协助我们
have come down from London to help us.
我跟你保证 我们会全力以赴
I assure you we're doing everything possible.
祝你好运 福尔摩斯先生
I wish you good luck, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢你 夫人
Oh thank you madam
我对你的损失深表遗憾
and my commiserations on your great loss.
我们肯定见过面吧？
Surely we've met?
之前在普利茅斯的游园会上
At a garden party in Plymouth some time ago.
没有 先生 你弄错了
No sir. You are mistaken.
不 我可是非常肯定的
No, do you know I could have sworn it.
你穿着一件浅灰色丝绸衣服
You wore a costume of dove-colored silk
上面有鸵鸟毛做的装饰物
with ostrich feather trimming.
我从来没有这样的衣服 先生
I never had such a dress, sir.
那就清楚了 谢谢你
That quite settles it. Thank you.
这就是挂着外套的灌木
That is the bush where the coat was hanging.
那天天气怎么样
What was the weather like?
没什么风 雨挺大
Wind calm bit of rain about.
那外套不是被风吹到灌木上 而是人挂的
And the coat was not blown against the bush but placed there?
哦 是的 是被人放的
Oh yes, it was placed.
督察
Inspector!
不 不 不好
No, no, no!
这片土地被太多人踏过
So many people have trampled around this land.
一定有很多人到过
There have been many people here.
那张垫子是故意摆在那里
That piece of matting has been placed there
供大家落脚的
and we have all stood upon there.
可老百姓不是
Not the general public.
我这个袋子里面有
I have in this bag.
约翰·斯特拉穿的一只靴子
One of the boots John Straker wore,
一只菲茨罗·伊辛普森的鞋子
one of Fitzroy Simpson's shoes,
一块银额马的马蹄铁
and a cast horseshoe of Silver Blaze.
谢谢你 督察
Thank you, Inspector.
燃了一半的蜡烛
Half burned wax candle.
不敢相信我居然忽视了它们
I cannot understand how I came to overlook them.
它们被埋在土里 自然看不见了
Oh they're invisible buried in the mud.
我能看见是因为我找的就是它们
I only saw them because I was looking for them.
什么 你早料到能发现它们？
What, you expected to find them?
我认为这并不是不可能的
I thought it not unlikely.
恐怕这里没有其他线索了
I'm afraid there are no more tracks.
周围一百码之内都检查过了
I've examined the ground for a hundred yards in every direction.
真是个愉快的夜晚啊
What a pleasant evening.
我想我要去散个步了 伸伸腿 华生
I think I'll take a walk, stretch my legs Watson?
没错
Yes, indeed.
这个我带走了 为了好运
I'll take this for luck.
之后罗斯上校会来接我们回塔维斯托克
I have some work to do in the house,
屋里还有事等着我做
then Colonel Ross is coming to take us back to Tavistock.
晚安 警官
Good evening, Constable.
假设银额马挣脱了缰绳
Suppose that Silver Blaze broke away,
那它会跑到哪里去呢？
where would he have gone?
如果它还在旷野上晃悠
If he'd run loose on the moor
到现在肯定会被人看到了
he'd have surely been seen by now.
可能那个吉普赛人的理论是正确的
Perhaps the gypsy theory's correct.
不 不 不 不
No, no, no, no.
马是非常喜欢群居的生物
A horse is a most gregarious creature.
既然它没有回到金斯皮兰
Now he did not go back to King's Pyland
自己的马厩 那就一定是去了…
to his own stable, so he must have gone…
梅普尔顿
to Mapleton.
现在我们以此为假设
Now let us use that as a working hypothesis.
这片土地十分干硬 但是那边的低洼地
The ground around here is very hard and dry, but over there
在星期一的晚上肯定是很湿润
in that hollow it must have been very wet on Monday night.
如果我们的假设是正确的
If our supposition is correct,
它肯定去过那里
he must have crossed it.
华生
Watson!
天 看看这个
By George, look at that.
你瞧见了想象力的可贵
You see the value of imagination
这正是格雷戈里督察缺少的一项资质
is the one quality which Inspector Gregory lacks.
我们想象可能发生的事情
We imagined what might have happened,
然后采取行动
acted upon the supposition,
最后发现是有道理的 让我们继续吧
and find ourselves justified. Let us proceed.
看 看
Look! Look!
马和人 都折回了
Horse and man turned.
（梅普尔顿驯马场 闲人禁入）
这里不准闲人逗留
No loitering around here.
你没长眼睛吗？
Haven't you got eyes in your head.
我只是想问你一个问题
I only wanted to ask you a question.
要是明天早晨五点我来拜访
Should I be too early to see Mr. Silas Brown,
西拉斯·布朗先生 会不会太早了
if I was to call around here at five-thirty tomorrow morning?
我不应该跟你说话
I shouldn't be speaking to you by rights.
给 男孩
Here lad.
请收下
please accept.
保佑你 先生
Bless you, sir.
您是位绅士
You're a gentleman.
布朗先生是这里起最早的
Mr. Brown's the early bird around here all right,
道森 你跟陌生人说三道四的干什么
Dawson, what are you doing gossiping with strangers?
干你自己的事去
Be about your business.
你们两个在这里想干什么
Now what the devil do you two want around here?
只占用你一点时间 布朗先生
Just a few minutes of your time, Mr. Brown.
离开这里 不然你就会被狗追着跑
Be off with you or you'll find the dog on your heels.
我为什么要和所有
Why should I talk
在这旷野上游荡的陌生人说话？
every gadabout stranger on the moor?
或许能让你免于 被布莱克沃特勋爵解雇
It may save you instant dismissal from Lord Blackwater's service
不会锒铛入狱
and the stiffest prison sentence.
留心周围
Keep guard.
星期二一大早
Early Tuesday morning,
你像平时一样巡视马场
you're about the yard as usual,
看见了一匹马在沼泽里
when you saw a horse on the moor.
等你靠近它时你意识到
When you approached it you realized
这完全不是一匹陌生的马
that it wasn't a strange horse at all.
是你熟知的一匹马 了如指掌
It was one that you knew, very well.
你的第一个反应就是带着银…
Your first instinct was to lead Silver…
银额马回到金斯皮兰
Silver Blaze back to King's Pyland
但是随即你有了 其他邪恶的想法
but then the devil put other ideas into your head.
你有了赚一笔大钱的机会
You have a chance to make a great deal of money.
你突然反应过来 如果把马藏起来…
It occurred to you that if you were to hide the horse…
你一直在看着我 对吧
You've been watching me, haven't you?
你在监视我 先生
You've been spying on me, sir.
那么 先生
Now. Sir.
你想让我做什么都行
I do what you want.
如果你要钱 会给你的
If it's money you want, you shall have it,
我怎么说你就怎么做
You will do exactly as I tell you.
我很少见到像西拉斯·布朗这样的
A more perfect compound of the bully, coward and sneak
集霸道 怯懦和狡猾 于一体的完美的组合
that Master Silas Brown. I've seldom met with.
那么说马在他那里？
He has the horse then?
当然
Of course.
但是他的马厩被搜过
But his stables have been searched.
像他这样的作假老手 知道很多伎俩
An old faker like him knows many a dodge.
华生 我不知道你是否注意到
Watson, I didn't know whether you observed
但是罗斯上校的举止有点傲慢
but Colonel Ross manner has been somewhat cavalier.
我想要对他开点玩笑
I'm inclined to have a little amusement at his expense.
不要向他透露任何马的事情
Say nothing to him about the horse.
没有你的允许 我什么都不会说
I shall say nothing without your permission.
非常好
Splendid.
从我们找到的线索来看 星期一晚上
We have found traces which show that a party of gypsies encamped
在凶案现场一英里之外
on Monday night within a mile of where
吉普赛人在露营开过派对
the murder took place.
菲茨罗·伊辛普森 可能跟他们商量好了
Fitzroy Simpson may well have an understanding with them
来把马藏起来
over hiding the horse.
尽管如此
Nevertheless, I think I owe it to the public
让银额马退出比赛 我依然觉得有愧于大家
to remove Silver Blaze's name for the entrance for the cup.
不 当然不行 上校 我会让这个名字留下
No, certainly not! Colonel, I should let the name stand.
但是我已经让贝阿得退出了
But I've already withdrawn Bayard.
但是我有把握 让银额马在星期六上场
But I have every hope that Silver Blaze will start on Saturday.
让你的骑师做准备吧
Have your jockey at readiness.
我很高兴听到你的观点 先生
I'm very glad to have your opinion, sir.
当然跟谁杀了
That is a minor point, of course,
约翰·斯特拉比这只是个次要问题
compared with the question of who killed John Straker.
毫无疑问你会专注于这个问题
Doubtless you will be devoting yourself to that problem.
正好相反 华生医生和我
On the contrary, Doctor Watson and I
会坐夜间特快回伦敦
were taking the Night Express to London.
我们已经呼吸过了你们这
We've had the most charming little
诱人的新鲜空气
breath of your country air.
所以你已经对缉拿杀害
So you've despaired already of
约翰·斯特雷克的凶手丧失信心了
arresting the murderer of poor John Straker.
困难重重
With our certain grave difficulties.
你有斯特拉克的照片吗
Do you have the photograph of Straker?
谢谢 督察 我已经准备好去塔维斯托克了
Thank you, Inspector. I am quite ready now for Tavistock.
留在这
Linger.
我必须说我对我们 伦敦的顾问非常失望
I must say I am rather disappointed in our London consultant.
我没有看到他来之后有任何的进展
I don't see that were any further than when he came.
但是至少他保证了
But at least you have his assurance Colonel
你的马可以参赛 上校
that your horse will run.
哦 是的 他是保证了
Oh yes, I have his assurance.
但我宁愿得到马
I should prefer to have the horse.
我觉得你应该采纳福尔摩斯先生的建议 上校
I think you should heed Mr. Holmes advice, Colonel.
看情况再说吧
Well I shall have to see.
不好意思 是谁在照看这些羊？
Excuse me, whom looks after these sheep?
是我 先生
I do, sir.
你有注意到它们最近有什么毛病吗
Have you noticed anything amiss of late?
没有 先生
No sir.
那也许算不上 但是有三只羊的脚跛了
Well it's not much account, but three of them have gone lame.
谢谢
Thank you.
大胆的推测 华生 很大胆的推测 你先请
A long shot, Watson, a very long shot. After you.
督察 我建议你注意下羊群中
Inspector I would like to recommend to you
这种奇异病症吧
the singular epidemic among the sheep.
你真的认为那很重要？
You really consider that to be important?
非常重要
Exceedingly so.
走了 贝恩斯
All right Baynes.
你还需要我注意其他
Is there any other point
一些问题吗 福尔摩斯先生？
to which you wish to draw my attention, Mr. Holmes?
那天夜里 狗的反应很奇怪
To the curious incident of the dog in the nighttime.
但是那天夜里 狗没什么反应啊
But the dog did nothing in the nighttime.
那正是奇怪的地方
That is the curious incident.
我的马到底在哪里 福尔摩斯？
Where the devil is my horse, Holmes?
不 不 不 不 它到底在哪？
No, no, no, no. Where the devil is he?
我猜 上校 如果你看见了 就可以认出它吧
I suppose, Colonel, that you would recognize him if you saw him?
认出我自己的马？
Know my own horse?
我在赛马场上活跃了二十年了
I have been on the turf for twenty years
以前从来没有被这么问过 这样该死的傻问题
and I've never been asked such a damn fool question before.
即使是一个孩子也知道
A child would know Silver Blaze
银额马的额头上有块白色的星型
with the white star on his forehead
后腿上有斑点
and mottled hind leg.
我想你能意识到如果我的马不上场
I suppose you realize if my horse doesn't run,
除了很可能会被人群报复
quite a part from being lynched by the crowd,
我还要去向赛马调查委员会自首
I shall be up before the Stewards.
可能会被每个英格兰的赛马场
Probably warned off every racecourse in England for life.
永远禁赛
Reputation ruined.
这是华生医生
Here's Doctor Watson.
而这匹 上校
And this, Colonel,
就是你的马
is your horse.
那不是我的马 福尔摩斯
But that's not my horse, Holmes!
我的天啊 你都干了些什么
Good God man, what have you done?
上校啊 这就是你的银额马
There Colonel is your Silver Blaze.
我从盗马贼手里发现了它
I found him in the hands of a faker
原封不动带回了这里
and brought him to the course just as he was.
老天爷
Good heavens.
你太让我激动了 福尔摩斯先生
You take my breath away, Mr. Holmes.
银额马
Silver Blaze.
如果它还参赛的话 就会赢得名次吧 阁下
If he runs me lord to win a place me lord?
当然会
To win, of course.
还有谁会像你吗？
Any more like you at home?
快点
Come on!
那匹该死的马到底是怎么回事啊
What's the matter with the damn horse?
福尔摩斯 你对它做了什么
What have you done to him Holmes?
它失去了当领跑者的本领
He seems to be missing his pacemaker.
我不应该让贝阿得退出
I should have never withdrawn Bayard.
等一下 他突破重围了
Wait a minute he's breaking through.
加油 银额马 加油 银额马
Come on Silver Blaze. Come on Silver Blaze.
快跑 快跑 快跑 快跑
Go on. Go on. Go on. Go on.
你创造了奇迹 福尔摩斯先生
You've done wonders Mr. Holmes,
我欠你几千个道歉
and I owe you a thousand apologies
因为我怀疑了你的能力
for having doubted your ability.
你找回了我的马 出色得完成了工作
Now you've done me a great service by recovering my horse.
如果你可以抓住杀害
You'd do me a greater still
约翰·斯特拉的凶手的话
if you could lay your hands on the murderer of John Straker.
我已经抓住了
I've done so.
什么？如果你已经得手 他现在人呢？
What? What's all this about if you got him. Where is he then?
他就在这里
He's here.
这里 哪里？
Here! Where?
此时… 此地
Some who's now present at this very moment.
是的 我很清楚
Yes, I quite recognize that
自己欠你一份人情 福尔摩斯先生
I'm under obligations to you Mr. Holmes,
但如果这不是一个非常烂的笑话
but this either a very bad joke
就是一种侮辱
or an insult.
哦 上校 真正的杀人犯 就站在你的后面
Oh the real murderer, Colonel, is Standing immediately behind you.
什么 这匹马
What the horse?
是的 这匹马
Yes, the horse.
如果我说它完全是自卫才这么做
And it may lessen his guilt if I say
也许可以减轻它的罪过
that it was done entirely in self-defense,
而且约翰·斯特拉这个人
and that John Straker
完全不值得你的信任
was a man quite unworthy of your trust.
四号 先生 第一名
Number four, sir, winner.
快来 罗斯
Come Ross.
好的 非常感谢
Yes, thank you very much.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
十二号
Number twelve.
我非常引以为豪 很骄傲
Very proud of it. Very proud.
非常感谢 谢谢
Thank you very much. Thank you.
我承认 先生们
I confess, gentlemen,
当我们来金斯皮兰的时候
when we came down to King's Pylan,
我曾经被说服了菲茨罗·伊辛普森 就是真凶
I was convinced that Fitzroy Simpson was the true culprit.
所有的报纸和警方的报告
All the newspaper and police reports
似乎都指向那一点
seemed to point to it.
直到我进入驯马师房里
It was only when I entered the trainer's house
想起了咖喱羊肉具有重要意义
that the immense significance of the curried mutton occurred to me.
我要承认即使到现在
I confess that even now.
我还不能明白它对我们有什么帮助
I cannot see how it helps us.
麻醉药 上校 绝对不会完全无味
Powdered opium, Colonel is by no means tasteless.
我说的对吗？
I am correct?
哦 完全正确 味道不至于难吃
Oh quite correct. The flavor is not distasteful
但是它是可以尝出来的
but it is perceptible.
如果它混在一般的饭菜里
Were it mixed with an ordinary dish
吃的人一定会发觉
the eater would undoubtedly detect it
可能就不会继续吃了
but would probably eat no more.
咖喱恰好 可以掩盖这股味道
Curry was exactly the medium with which to disguise the taste.
所以那一定是斯特拉克或者是他的妻子
So it must have been Straker or his wife?
没错
Exactly.
我想起来你提起过狗
Cause I remember you spoke of a dog.
是的 那只晚上没有吠叫的狗
Yes, the dog that didn't bark in the night.
有人走进了马厩
Well someone had been into the stable
并且牵走了马 狗却没有叫
and taken out the horse and the dog had not barked.
所以很明显这个午夜访客 是狗很熟悉的人
So obviously this midnight visitor was someone the dog knew well.
我本来就不相信会是陌生人
I wasn't really convinced that it was a stranger.
但是为了什么
But for what purpose should he take out the horse, and
显然他是个大骗子
A dishonest one, obviously.
之前就有过驯马师
There have been cases before now
把赌注下在
where trainers have made great sums of money by
自己马的败北上
laying against their own horses
然后从中作梗而赚下一大笔
and then preventing them from winning.
有时候故意找个骑术不佳的骑师
Well sometimes you get a pulling jockey, I will say that.
最狡诈的方式
by surer and most subtler means.
这把…
This…
奇特的刀 是在死者的手上发现的
singular knife, it was found in the dead man's hand
正常人不会用它当作武器 对吧？
and which no sane man would use as a weapon, right?
哦 是的 只有…
Oh yes, only,
只有在最精密的手术里才会使用
only used in the most delicate operations.
它那天晚上是用在了一个很精密的手术上
It was used for a very delicate operation that night.
不好意思
Excuse me.
如你所知 上校
As you know, Colonel,
凭你丰富的赛马经验
with your wide knowledge of turf matters
在马的后踝骨腱子肉上 从皮下划一小道
that it is possible to make a slight nick in the horse's tendon,
轻轻的伤口
and do it, subcutaneously.
轻微的跛足 会被认为是训练过度
Any slight lameness will be put down to a strain in training
或是挫伤 不会被想到是一个肮脏的阴谋
or bruised, never foul play.
恶棍 该死的无赖
Villain! The damn Scoundrel!
手术不能在马厩里进行 我不要吃的
Not an operation to be done in the stable. No food for me.
马这么敏感的生物 会吵醒熟睡的人
So sensitive a creature would arouse the soundest of sleepers.
我和格雷戈里都瞎了眼
I've been blind and Gregory too.
怪不得他需要蜡烛 还有划过的火柴
Of course, that's why he needed the candle and struck the match.
当我检查随身物品时
When I examined Straker's belongings
我非常幸运地不仅发现了
I was fortunate enough to discover
他的犯罪方法 还有犯罪动机
not only the method of the crime but also the motive.
大部分人不会
Most men do not
把别人的账单 放进自己的口袋里
carry other people's bills in their pockets.
从这点我总结出
From this I concluded that
斯特拉克是过着双重身份的生活
Straker was leading a double life.
那账单的种类可以看出
The nature of the bill shows
这个案子里有一个女人
that there was a woman in the case.
而且是一个喜欢昂贵东西的女人
And a woman of expensive taste.
尽管你对你的仆人很大方
Liberal though you are with your servants,
我很确定他们也承受不起
I'm sure they're not able to afford
花二十二几尼为女人买件衣服
twenty-two guinea, walking dresses for their ladies.
照斯特拉克夫人的说法
Mrs. Straker never had
她从来没有这样的衣服
one by her own admission.
第二天早上我去邦德街
When I visited Bond Street the other morning,
把斯特拉克的照片 给莱苏丽尔夫人时
I showed Madame Lesurier this photograph of Straker.
她认出了他
She recognized him
他是一位很好的顾客
as an extremely good customer
叫威廉 德比郡
called William Derbyshire
有一位非常时髦的年轻妻子
with a very dashing young wife
她非常偏爱昂贵的裙子
with a partiality for expensive dresses.
女人 女人
Women! Women!
我想是她
I suppose it was she who plunged him head over heels into debt
斯特拉克把银额马领到低洼地
Straker let out Silver Blaze into the hollow
在那里 他的烛光不会被马场的人看见
where his light would not be visible from the yard.
辛普森在逃跑中 落下了围巾
Simpson in his flight had dropped his scarf
斯特拉克捡起了它 毫无疑问
Straker picked it up with the idea, no doubt
他是要用 绑住马腿
that he might use it in securing the horses leg.
斯特拉克把蜡烛点着了
Straker was able to light his candle
但是就在他准备动刀时 马突然给
but just as he had the knife ready the horse lashed out
他的额头来了致命一击
and caught him a fatal blow on the forehead
为什么？为什么马会突然发起攻击呢？
Why? And why did the horse lash out so suddenly?
是被蜡烛 还是刀吓着了？
Frightened by the candle, the knife?
动物有一种奇怪的本能
Well animals have a strange instinct.
它们似乎知道 谁不怀好意
They seem to know when some mischief is intended.
我必须承认 我最后的推测非常大胆
My final shot I must confess, was a long one.
我突然想到 像斯特拉克这样精明的人
It struck me that such astute man, as Straker
在进行马腱手术之前一定做过练习
would not undertake this tendon-nicking without a little practice.
那些羊 没错
The sheep! Of course!
太精彩了 亲爱的
Wonderful, my dear.
现在你只剩下一件事没有解释
Now you've explained all but one thing.
那匹马 马在哪里？
The horse. Now where was the horse?
在这方面
Well I think we must have
我们必须要宽容一点 上校
a little amnesty in that direction, Colonel.
它在外面被你其中一位邻居照顾着
It bolted and was looked after by one of your neighbors.
先生们我现在为你们献上一段祝酒词
Gentlemen I give you a toast
献给银额马
to Silver Blaze
以我的朋友
coupled with the names of my friends,
夏洛克·福尔摩斯先生和华生医生之名
Mr. Sherlock Holmes and Doctor Watson.
敬银额马
To Silver Blaze.